Guide to the Konstanty Jeleński Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Konstanty Jeleński papers
1940-1988
GEN MSS 676
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.43
(18 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, writings and other material that documents Konstanty Jeleński's editorial work, literary criticism and involvement with several cultural organizations, including the Congress for Cultural Freedom, the Royaumont Foundation, and the Institut national de l'audiovisuel. A significant portion of the papers documents Jeleński's translation and criticism of the writings of Witold Gombrowicz. The Papers are not a complete literary archive of Jeleński's life and work and contain only a portion of his correspondence and writings. Series I consists chiefly of Jeleński's general correspondence, writings and writings of others; the remaining series consist of papers related to specific topics and organizations. Correspondents include Witold and Rita Gombrowicz, fellow affilates with the Congress for Cultural Freedom, and publishers. Essays and other writings relate chiefly to mid-twentieth-century Polish literary and political life (especially that of Polish émigrés), to the activities of the Congress for Cultural Freedom, and to Jeleński's translations from Polish to French. Printed material relates to literary, historical and political topics, especially in Poland in the mid- to late- twentieth century. A small amount of material relates to Jeleński's affiliation with the Royaumont Foundation and the Institut national de l'audiovisuel, documenting a portion of the activity of these organizations in the 1970s and 1980s.
Jeleński, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander), 1922-1987
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 19 contains Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Institut Littéraire on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1989, and gift of Richard Overstreet and the estate of Leonor Fini, 2001.
Konstanty Jeleński, 1922-1987
Konstanty Aleksander Jeleński (in French: Constantin Jelenski) was born January 2, 1922 in Warsaw, Poland and died May 4, 1987 in Paris, France. At the age of eighteen he left Poland to serve the Polish Army in France. He lived the remainder of his life as an émigré, first in Italy for several years after the Second World War, then settling in Paris in 1951.
In Paris, Jeleński was active in Polish émigré literary circles. He led the Eastern European division of the Congress for Cultural Freedom (after 1967, the International Association for Cultural Freedom) and was a prolific contributor to the Association's monthly publication Preuves and to Kultura, the Polish émigré literary journal. Beginning in 1975, he became increasingly active with the Institut national de l'audiovisuel.
Jeleński's criticism, translations and edited works addresses a wide range of literary, political and artistic topics, especially twentieth-century Polish literature and history. Among his most influential works are many critical essays about Witold Gombrowicz and the edited volume Anthologie de la poesie polonaise (1965).
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, writings and other material that documents Konstanty Jeleński's editorial work, literary criticism and involvement with several cultural organizations, including the Congress for Cultural Freedom, the Royaumont Foundation, and the Institut national de l'audiovisuel. A significant portion of the papers documents Jeleński's translation and criticism of the writings of Witold Gombrowicz. The papers are not a complete literary archive of Jeleński's life and work and contain only a portion of his correspondence and writings. Series I consists chiefly of Jeleński's general correspondence, writings and writings of others; the remaining series consist of papers related to specific topics and organizations. Correspondents include Witold and Rita Gombrowicz, fellow affiliates with the Congress for Cultural Freedom, and publishers. Essays and other writings relate chiefly to mid-twentieth-century Polish literary and political life (especially that of Polish émigrés), to the activities of the Congress for Cultural Freedom, and to Jeleński's translations from Polish to French. Printed material relates to literary, historical and political topics, especially in Poland in the mid- to late-twentieth century. A small amount of material relates to Jeleński's affiliation with the Royaumont Foundation and the Institut national de l'audiovisuel, documenting a portion of the activity of these organizations in the 1970s and 1980s.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. General Papers of Konstanty Jeleński, 1940-1988. II. Papers Relating to Witold Gombrowicz, 1951-1987. III. Papers Relating to the Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1959-1976. IV. Papers Relating to the Royaumont Foundation, 1970-1973. V. Papers Relating to the Institut national de l'audiovisuel, 1979-1984.
Polish literature; Authors, Polish; Poland -- Intellectual life -- 1918-1945; Poland -- History -- 1945-1980; Poland -- Intellectual life -- 1945-1989; Europe -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; France -- Emigration and immigration; Poland -- Emigration and immigration; Jeleński, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander), 1922-1987; Gombrowicz, Witold, 1904-1969; Congress for Cultural Freedom; Institut national de l'audiovisuel (France); Royaumont Foundation (France)
- General Papers of Konstanty Jeleński, 1940-1988; Series I; 1.88; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I. is organized into five subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Writings of Others, Visual Material, and Printed Material.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I documents Jeleński's work as a writer, translator and editor and includes correspondence, writings, visual material and printed material. Correspondents include Witold and Rita Gombrowicz, various publishers, and literary colleagues. Writings include drafts of essays on literature and politics, and writings of others on political and literary issues, focusing on Eastern Europe from the late 1950s through the early 1980s. Visual material includes a portrait of Jeleński in pencil by Bernard Perlin. Printed material includes clippings and copies of articles on policitical and literary issues in Europe in the early 1980s.
  - Correspondence
    Letters are incoming unless otherwise indicated. Outgoing letters are chiefly carbon copies.
    - Academic Press, Inc.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich
    - Athanäum Verlag, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Audiberti, Jacques, 1964 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bondy, François, outgoing, 1975-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Burnshaw, Stanley, 1972 -1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chiaromonte, Nicola, outgoing, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Daedalus, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - de Roux, Dominique, incoming and outgoing, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dönhoff, Marion Gräfin, outgoing, 1984
    - Editions de l'Herne, 1971 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Editions l'Age d'Homme, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fiszman, Samuel, 1974 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Flamand, Paul, 1976 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Gombrowicz, Rita, incoming and outgoing, 1965-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes copies of correspondence between Rita Gombrowicz and Jarosław Iwaszkiewicz.
    - Gombrowicz, Witold, 1958-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13-17)
    - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, incoming and outgoing, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Herbert, Zbigniew, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Huberman, A. Michael, 1971 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Institut littéraire, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Iwaszkiewicz, Jarosław, 1964 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Josselson, Michael, incoming and outgoing, 1961, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - [Kieniewicz, Stefan?], 1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Kirchner, Hanna, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Kott, Jan, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Malić, Zdravko, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - McCarthy, Mary, outgoing, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Miłosz, Czesław, incoming and outgoing, 1964, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - Mitterrand, François, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Nadeau, Maurice, outgoing, 1958 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Radio Free Europe, 1969, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Seminar Press
    - Sperber, Manès, outgoing, holograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Stone, Shepard, incoming and outgoing, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Ulam, Adam, 1971 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Wydawnictwo Literackie, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Includes contracts.
    - Various publishers, correspondence and contracts, 1958-1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - _____, Adam, outgoing, 1975 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - _____, Livio, outgoing, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Unidentified, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title. Unidentified texts are filed at the end of the listing.
    Jeleński's writings on Gombrowicz are filed in Series II.
    - "Adam Zagajewski: Cienka kreska ( Le trait mince )," typescript, corrected, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "L'aigle d'her, aujourd'hui," typescript carbon, [1961] (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "Andrzej Szcypiorski, Msza za miasto Arras," typescript, signed, corrected (and copy), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "Au-dela de la Chapelle Sixtine et du masque de la Cote d'Ivoire," printed version, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "La bete au bois-dormant," typescript (copy), corrected, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - "Chronique de Poznan, typescript (and copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "Comment peut-on être polonais?" typescript (copies), 1980s (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "A Dialectical Paradox," proof, corrected (copy), undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - "Le dictateur anachronique," typescript and notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "En Pologne, ou desormais partout?" typescript, corrected, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - "Europe: a reversal of historical perspectives," typescript carbon, corrected, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - "Extraits de la lettre d'Andrzej Wajda à C. Jelenski, dateé du 16.9.82," holograph, circa 1982 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "La fin de Po prostu ," typescript (and copy), undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - "Interview de Maria Kusner," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "Jan Lebenstein, peintre des mythes de la nature humaine," typescript (copy) and printed version, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - "Jerzy Andrzejewski: Miazga," typescript, corrected (and photocopy), 1980s (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Kazimierz Brandys: Miesiace ( Les mois )," typescript (copies), corrected, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "Kazimierz Heutschel: Liturgie ," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "Leszek Kolakowski: Rozmówy z Diablem ( Conversations avec le Diable )," typescript, corrected (copy), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "List do Redakji Kultury ," holograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - "La Maison d'Ernst Fuchs," typescript (copy), corrected, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "The making of Central Europe," typescript and holograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "Mihail Chemiakin," typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "Mówmy o emigracji" (transcript of audio recording), typescript (copy), 1986 November 4 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "A Note on Beauford Delaney," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - "Notes on conversations with Adam Schaff," typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - "Un nouveau poete de l'absurde," typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - "Nouveaux borborygmes," typescript carbon, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - "Poland and Europe," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - "La Pologne Post-Stalinienne," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - "La 'Raison d'Etat' ne date pas d'hier," typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - "Revisionisme ou pragmatisme," typescript, corrected, circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - "S. I. Witkiewicz, un Polonais aux sources du XX siecle," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "Stanislaw Vincenz," typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - "Three lectures on the literature of disenchantment," typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - "L'univers parallele de Michel Henricot," typescript (copy), corrected and "Michel Henricot," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - "Zofia Romanowicz: Na Wyspie ( Dans l'Île )," typescript (copies), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Untitled essay on Balthus (Balthasar Klossowski), holograph and typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Untitled essay on Roland Cat, typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Untitled essays on Pornografia and Kosmos by Witold Gombrowicz, holograph, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Untitled text on the book of Job, holograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Untitled text on Alibi by Elsa Morante, holograph, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Untitled text on Nabokov, holograph, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Untitled text on C. Norwid and S. I. Witkiewicz, holograph, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Notes on nationalism, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Notes on Polish history and economy, undated (Box 3, Folder 89-90)
    - Notes on Pierre Bourdieu, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Questionnaire for Czesław Miłosz, typescript (copy), undated (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Unidentified essays and fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 93-113)
    - Photocopies and offprints of printed essays, 1961-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Writings of Others
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Baudrillard, Jean, "Simulacre et science fiction," typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Cazes, Bernard, "La prospective face à l'imprevu," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - L'Express, interview with Marek Hlasko, typescript carbon, undated (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Franklin, H. Bruce, "La littérature d'anticipation de l'avenir," typescript, corrected, with letter from Oxford University Press, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Gombrowicz, Rita, "Temoignage de Constantin Jelenski," holograph (copy), undated (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Henczel, Kazimierz, "Konstantemu Jeleńskiemu" (poem), typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Herbert, Zbigniew, "Envoi de Monsieur Cogito," typescript (copy), undated (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Herling-Grudziński, Gustaw, "Journal écrit de nuit," typescript (copies), 1982 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Karpinski, Wojciech, "Les essais de Jelenski" [French translation by Jeleński?], typescript (copy), 1981 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Krasiński, Zygmunt, "Nie-boska komedja," French translation by Jeleński, holograph, with printed version of Polish original, photocopy, and typewritten note, undated (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Kultura, "Le prix littéraire de Kultura ... décerné à Constantin Jelenski pour 1981," typescript (and copy) (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Piattelli-Palmarini, Massimo, "Conversazione con Jacques Monod," typescript, printed version and notes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Spinelli, Altiero, "Intervention de M. Altiero Spinelli," typescript (copy), undated (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Various authors, Polish writings in French translation, typescript, corrected, 1956-1957, undated (Box 5, Folder 128-139)
      Many of the Polish versions were originally printed in Po prostu.
  - Visual Material
    - Portrait of Jeleński in pencil, by unidentified artist, 1940 June 17 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Portrait of Jeleński in pencil, by Bernard Perlin, 1949 June 29 (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Photograph of Pope John Paul II inscribed to Jeleński, 1980
    - Drawings, possibly illustrations for articles (copies), undated
  - Printed Material
    - General clippings and copies of articles, 1981-1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 142)
- Papers Relating to Witold Gombrowicz, 1951-1987; Series II; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Witold and Rita Gombrowicz Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers.
  Series II consists of material collected by Jeleński in relation to his critical and editorial work on Gombrowicz and translations of Gombrowicz's writings into French. Several of the writings consist of translations into French, most likely all by Jeleński. The bulk of the series consists of drafts or copies of critical essays about Gombrowicz, by Jeleński and by others. The subseries Other Papers includes a few documents and contracts related to the publishing of Gombrowicz's writings and newspaper clippings on Gombrowicz.
  - Witold and Rita Gombrowicz correspondence
    Unless otherwise indicated, material filed under this heading is photocopies. Dates reflect the original correspondence. Correspondence dated after Witold Gombrowicz's death in 1969 is with Rita Gombrowicz.
    - Bondy, François, incoming and outgoing, 1961-1967 (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Bourgois, Christian, outgoing, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Buber, Martin, incoming, 1951-1955 (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - de Roux, Dominique, outgoing, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - Jeleński, Konstanty, incoming (originals and copies), 1958-1969 (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Murat, Napoleon, outgoing, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Nowak, Jan, incoming and outgoing, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - Pineda,Virgilio, outgoing, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Sandauer, Artur, outgoing, 1956-1964 (Box 6, Folder 151-152)
    - Schulz, Bruno, outgoing, undated (Box 6, Folder 153)
    - Unidentified, outgoing (copies), 1968 (Box 6, Folder 154)
  - Writings
    The Writings subseries is organized under several headings: Writings of Witold Gombrowicz, Interviews with Witold Gombrowicz, Writings of Konstanty Jeleński on Gombrowicz, and Writings of Others on Gombrowicz.
    - Writings of Witold Gombrowicz
      Arranged alphabeticlly by title. Untitled material is filed at the end of the listing.
      - "Bruno Schultz et Ferdydurke," holograph (copy), with notes by Jeleński, undated
      - "Gombrowicz et les Polonais," holograph (copy), with typewritten note, undated
      - Kosmos, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 6, Folder 155-156)
      - "Lettres à Bruno Schultz," typescript carbon, undated (Box 6, Folder 157)
      - "Mickiewicz et la beauté polonaise," typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 6, Folder 158)
      - "Mon voyage italien," typescript (copy), undated (Box 6, Folder 159)
      - Operetka
        - Polish language version, holograph (copy), corrected, undated (Box 6, Folder 160)
        - French translation by Jeleński ( Operette ), holograph and typescript, corrected by Gombrowicz, undated (Box 6, Folder 161-163)
        - Copies of manuscripts and documents related to Operetka, undated (Box 7, Folder 164)
        - Program for a Theatre National Populaire production of Operette, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 165)
      - "Souvenirs Polonais," holograph and typescript (copies), undated (Box 7, Folder 166-167)
      - "Stanisław-Ignacy Witkiewicz," Polish and French versions, typescript carbon, undated (Box 7, Folder 168)
      - "Wspomnienia polskie," typescript (copy), undated (Box 7, Folder 169)
      - Curriculum Vitae, holograph, circa 1967 (Box 7, Folder 170)
      - Radio broadcasts, typescript (copies), undated (Box 7, Folder 171-173)
    - Interviews with Witold Gombrowicz
      - "Interview avec Witold Gombrowicz," typescript, corrected, 1969 July (Box 7, Folder 174)
      - "Witold Gombrowicz, derniere interview," typescript carbon, 1969 September (Box 7, Folder 175)
      - [Sanavio, Piero?], notes from an interview in Italian, typescript (copy), undated (Box 7, Folder 176)
    - Writings of Konstanty Jeleński on Gombrowicz
      Arranged alphabetically by title.
      - "Biographie de Witold Gombrowicz," typescript (copy), 1960s (Box 7, Folder 177)
      - "La cargaison clandestine d'un navire corsaire," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 7, Folder 178)
      - "De la patrie a la F[?]," holograph (and copy), undated (Box 7, Folder 179)
      - "De L'Histoire a Opérette ," typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 7, Folder 180)
      - "Extraits du journal de Witold Gombrowicz a traduire en francais," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 181-182)
      - "Gombrowicz et la Pologne," holograph (and copy), undated (Box 7, Folder 183)
      - "Gombrowicz et Sandauer," typescript, corrected and notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 184-185)
      - " L'Histoire, une piece inconnue de Gombrowicz," typescript, corrected, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 186-187)
      - L'Histoire (introduction), holograph, undated (Box 7, Folder 188)
      - "Lettre de Witold Gombrowicz a Maria Paczowska," holograph (copy), undated (Box 7, Folder 189)
      - "Odpowiedz na ankietę o Gombrowiczu," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7, Folder 190)
      - "La Pologne dans le theátre de Gombrowicz," holograph, undated (Box 7, Folder 191)
      - "Preface de l' edition allemande (with François Bondy)," typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 7, Folder 192)
      - "Die Tagebucher von Witold Gombrowicz," typescript carbon, undated (Box 7, Folder 193)
      - "Witold Gombrowicz," printed version, corrected, and notes by Jeleński, undated (Box 7, Folder 194)
      - "Witold Gombrowicz" (with François Bondy), typescript (copy), corrected, undated (Box 7, Folder 195)
      - "Witold Gombrowicz, le drame et l'anti-drame," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 8, Folder 196)
      - Notes on L'Histoire, typescript (copy) and holograph, undated (Box 8, Folder 197-198)
      - Notes on Gombrowicz manuscripts, holograph (and copy), undated (Box 8, Folder 199)
      - Notes on Trans-Atlantique, holograph (and copy), undated (Box 8, Folder 200)
      - Notes on "Witold Gombrowicz, świat jego młodości," by Tadeusz Kepinski, holograph, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 201)
      - Notes on "Gombrowicz, la forme e il rito," by Piero Sanavio, holograph, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 202)
      - General notes on Gombrowicz, 1970s (Box 8, Folder 203-206)
    - Writings of Others on Gombrowicz
      Arranged alphabetically by author. Unidentified material is filed at the end of the listing.
      - Bauer, Volker K, Der Tanz, Farce phantastique in drei Akten nach Witold Gombrowicz, typescript, (copy), 1980 (Box 8, Folder 207)
      - Beers, Paul, essay on Gombrowicz," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 8, Folder 208)
      - Benoit, Jeannin, [contribution to the Cahier de l'Herne on Gombrowicz], typescript, undated (Box 8, Folder 209)
      - Betelu, Mariano, "Para Witolda," French translation by Jeleński, holograph, circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 210)
      - Bloch-Michel, Jean, review of Cosmos, typescript carbon (and copy), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 211)
      - Błonski, Jan, " L'Histoire et Opérette ," French translation by Jeleński, holograph, undated (Box 8, Folder 212)
      - Bondy, François
        - "Ein polonischer Abgesang," typescript carbon, undated (Box 8, Folder 213)
        - [Bondy, François?], "Ein Theater der Peinlichkeit," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 8, Folder 214)
      - Brandys, Kazimierz, essay on Gombrowicz, manuscript, undated (Box 8, Folder 215)
      - Brodsky, David, "Witold Gombrowicz, Artist-hero of contemporary metaphysics," typescript (and copy), undated (Box 8, Folder 216)
      - Cahiers de l'Herne, issue on Gombrowicz, notes, proofs and related correspondence, circa 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 217-222)
      - Cataluccio, Francesco, "I 'tentativi' di Gombrowicz," typescipt (copy), 1983 (Box 8, Folder 223)
        Includes a letter from Cataluccio to Jeleński.
      - Chwin, Stefan, "Gombrowicz i maska," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 8, Folder 224)